<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The state of the Church of Rome when the Reformation began as it appears by the advice given to Paul III and Julius III by creatures of their own : with a preface leading to the matter of the book.</title>
            <author>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33223</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4400</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15337</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12950746</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12950746</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95895</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33223)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95895)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 733:45)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The state of the Church of Rome when the Reformation began as it appears by the advice given to Paul III and Julius III by creatures of their own : with a preface leading to the matter of the book.</title>
                  <author>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Rogers ..., and Samuel Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to W. Clagett. cf. NUC pre-1956, DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Paul --  III, --  Pope, 1468-1549.</term>
               <term>Julius --  III, --  Pope, 1487-1555.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Reformation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:95895:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oct.</hi> 24. 1687.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Liber cui Titulus</hi> [The State of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> when the Reformation began, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] H. Maurice, <hi>R. in C. P. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wilhelmo <hi>Archiepiſc. Cant. a Sacris.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95895:1"/>
            <p>THE STATE OF THE Church of Rome WHEN THE Reformation Began, As it appears by the ADVICES GIVEN TO <hi>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L</hi> III. and <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> III. BY Creatures of their Own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a Preface leading to the Matter of the Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>William Rogers</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> over againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> and <hi>Samuel Smith</hi> at the <hi>Princes Arms</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, MDCLXXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:95895:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95895:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>THE oppoſition that <hi>Luther</hi> made to Indulgences at first, and ſoon after to other Abuſes in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, awakened many to enquire into the Reaſons of ſeveral things in which they had hitherto acquieſced without particular examination: Which liberty ſo dangerous to the interest of the <hi>Roman</hi> See, ſoon brought upon <hi>Luther,</hi> who was ſo notable an example of it, no little trouble from thence; inſomuch that be found himſelf conſtrained to appeal to a General Council: An expedient no leſs hated by the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> which had not yet forgotten the Councils of <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Baſil,</hi> than it was generally deſired by all the better ſort of men, as before for the reforming of Abuſes, ſo now for the quieting of Controverſies in Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leo</hi> the Xth being dead, who had not been wanting, for his part, to ſuppreſs theſe beginnings of a new Inquiſition into the Authority of Popes, was ſucceeded by <hi>Adrian</hi> VI, about four Years after <hi>Luther</hi>'s Declaration. <hi>Adrian</hi> like an hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est man, ingenuouſly confeſſed that this diſtreſs was juſtly come upon the Holy See, as a puniſhment of thoſe Abominations that had been committed in it, and promiſed to the World a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. But the <hi>German</hi> Princes inſiſted to have a Free and General Council called; which was by no means well ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> Whereupon the Secular Princes ſent their <hi>Manifeſto</hi> to the Pope of the <hi>Centum Gravamina,</hi> or the hundred Grievances which they had ſuffered from that Court. But <hi>Adrian</hi> died (not without vehement ſuſpition of
<pb facs="tcp:95895:3"/>foul play) before he had ſat two Years in the Chair, and with him died almost all that was honest and good in the <hi>Roman</hi> Court.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clement</hi> VII comes next to the Papacy, who of all things could not endure the thoughts of a General Council, in times wherein he was ſure the Popes Authority would be called in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: He therefore laboured against it with all imaginable induſtry and artifice. But it being impoſſible to ſatisfy thoſe that had not yet openly withdrawn themſelves from the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of that See, without ſeeming to condeſcend to the general deſire of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> in this matter, he tried at length to pacifie them, by making promiſes of calling a Council, which it was plain to wiſe men he never intended to perform; ſince at first he would neither ſay where nor when it ſhould be held; and at length, when the Emperour preſſed hard upon him, he abſolutely inſiſted, that the Council might be held in <hi>Italy:</hi> A condition, which as things then ſtood, he was ſure would not be ſubmitted to.</p>
            <p>Then comes <hi>Paul</hi> III, as great a Diſſembler as ever lived, who knew no leſs than his Predeceſſours how fatal ſuch a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil as was deſired, must neceſſarily be to the Gentlemen of the <hi>Roman</hi> See. He found that it was but more paſſionately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, for being refuſed; and was indeed put to the utmost ſtretch of his Talent to keep a temper in ſo difficult a caſe: But being the fittest perſon in the World to do what was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in this nice Juncture; he put off, for ſome time, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of a Council, under the pretence of an earnest deſire to call one: but when that artifice was ſtale, he delaied the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening of it after it was called: And when nothing elſe would do, he knew the best ways how to manage and govern it, and to make the World believe all the while that it was uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd and free.</p>
            <p>But in the third Year of his Popedom, the clamour of the World being upon him for neither calling a Council, nor ſo much as performing his promiſe of Reforming the Court and the
<pb facs="tcp:95895:3"/>Church himſelf, he was forced to make ſome notable ſemblance of the later, that he might a little longer keep off the former. To this end he required four Cardinals, and five other Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, to draw up, in the most impartial manner, a formal Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of Abuſes that needed a Reformation: Which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly was done in the former of the two following Advices that are here publiſhed.</p>
            <p>The trick was to make the Chriſtian Princes believe, that he that required, and they who gave this Advice were in good earnest: And ſo it was ſent into <hi>Germany,</hi> where it produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced quite other effects then were hoped from it; for all mens mouths were opened against the Court more than they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: And the Court ſoon ſhewed, that this ſolemn Advice was but meer Artifice and Colluſion to amuſe the World. and to keep off the ſo-much-dreaded Council, as long as it was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. As for the Pope himſelf, how well he was diſpoſed to follow the Rules of this Advice, appeared by the whole courſe of things afterwards: For his buſineſs all along was to ſupport the Abſoluteneſs of the <hi>Roman</hi> See; and to maintain, that <hi>all Judgment in matters of Religion, ought to be referred to the Apoſtolic See, and that Divine and Humane Laws; and the Conſent of Ages had given to the Pope the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Authority, as of calling Councils, ſo of determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ordering things that regard the Unity and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Church.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Padr. Pael. Aug.</hi> 5. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſome Copies; 24. 1544.</note> As he told the Emperour roundly in a Letter to him about ſeven Years after.</p>
            <p>As for the Courtiers that gave the Advice, one of them was the <hi>Theatine</hi> Cardinal, <hi>John Peter Caraffa,</hi> who was eighteen Years after Pope by the name of <hi>Paul</hi> IV; and who therefore had it in his power to put the Counſel he gave to <hi>Paul</hi> III, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to execution, if any ſuch thing had been in his mind. But no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be more inconſiſtent with his Counſel, than his Practice was: The Advice acknowledged, that the unbounded Licentiouſneſs of Popes in breaking Laws, and doing whatever they had amind to do, had reduced <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> to its deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="tcp:95895:4"/>condition. But this man yielded not to any of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours in Pride and lawleſs Liberty: He vouchſafed not to allow Secular Princes fit to be his Companions: He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan his Papacy with breaking the Oath of Capitulation, uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally made in the Conclave; and upon that occaſion, declared it to be an Article of Faith, That the Pope could not be bound: He made himſelf ſo odious to the World, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to the Citizens of <hi>Rome,</hi> by Perfidiouſneſs and Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that the rage of the People against his Name and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, could not be appeaſed, but by doing the moſt publick diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graces to him after he was dead.</p>
            <p>Now whether <hi>Paul</hi> IV, when Cardinal, gave ſome good Advice for faſhion ſake, or having had ſome good purpoſes once, laid them all aſide when he came to be Pope, I ſhall not diſpute: But 'tis a plain caſe, that theſe men have confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed most horrible Scandals against themſelves; and that at a time when their obligations to reform them, were the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est that the World could lay upon them, they moved not one ſtep towards a Reformation in good earnest; but made it their buſineſs to baffle the deſires and hopes of all good men: Which ſhewed it to be the vainest thing imaginable, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect afterwards any Reformation by a Council under the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the <hi>Roman</hi> Court, which by their own confeſſion was guilty of all the diſorders of the Church, or of ſuch Popes as thoſe, who by their own confeſſion had been the chiefest Malefactors. The Decrees of an <hi>Italian</hi> Council under the Direction of ſuch Managers as theſe, were not likely to be very holy ones. Nor were matters of Doctrine in a fair way to be ſincerely delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated upon, and determined truly by thoſe who could not be brought to mend the most notorious faults they confeſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst themſelves; not ſuch points of Doctrine, to be ſure, as ſerved to ſupport thoſe Abuſes in practiſe, which they were reſolved not to Reform.</p>
            <p>Certainly there could be no other Reaſon to imagine that the Grace of the Holy Ghost ſhould be preſent with ſuch a Council,
<pb facs="tcp:95895:4"/>excepting this only, that the Managers were brought to it with as much difficulty, as if they had been ſure to meet the Holy Ghost there.</p>
            <p>The Bull for intimation of the Council, was not Publiſhed till five Years after the Advice. Nor was it reſolved that they ſhould begin till two Years after that, when the Pope fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed his Legates with Powers to Diſſolve it,
<note place="margin">Hiſtory of Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> p. 112.</note> if it ſhould not be an Obedient Council. For no Man could certainly ſay with what Diſpoſitions, or in what Numbers, the <hi>German, French,</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Biſhops might come, and it was good to provide against the worst. It was yet about a year before the Council was opened; and the Proceedings were then retarded by arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial Difficulties, as well as accidental ones; and with all the Management, it did not throughly pleaſe; and ſo after frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Pretences was in two Years time by a Majority of Votes, Tranſlated to <hi>Bolonia,</hi> the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> remaining ſtill in <hi>Trent.</hi> The <hi>Papalins</hi> must have it nearer home that they might tend it the better. But do what they could, they were obliged three Years after to reaſſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>Trent,</hi> the loſs of which Point was therefore to be ſupplied with other Arts.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Paul</hi> Dying at this time, was ſucceeded by <hi>Julius</hi> III. who thought fit to ſuſpend the Council for two Years, the effect of which was that it came not together till ten Years after. As for the Motives that influenced theſe Councils, and the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices that brought them to effect, and the Intrigues with Princes, and the Advantages which the Court made of their oppoſite Intereſts, for bringing, the Council to a good end; all this is to be ſeen in Father <hi>Paul</hi>'s Hiſtory, but the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars are too many to be touched here.</p>
            <p>It was to <hi>Julius</hi> III that the three Biſhops at <hi>Bononia</hi> Addreſſed the Second Advice, as <hi>Vergerius</hi> relates this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who best knew it, not to <hi>Paul</hi> the third, as <hi>Wolfius</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers in his <hi>Lectiones Memorabiles,</hi> who though he Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Vergerius,</hi> had lighted upon a falſe Copy, in which that paſſage at the end of the Advice, concerning our Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:95895:5"/>was left out, which would have diſcovered that miſtake of his, from whomſoever he had it, that it was found in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, after the Death of <hi>Paul</hi> III. Certainly the diſcovery of this Advice was the most Fatal Thing that ever happened to the Reputation of the <hi>Roman</hi> Cauſe. And if it had not been upon the File against them now for above an hundred Years, I make no queſtion but the Popiſh Gentlemen of this Age, would run it down for a <hi>Sham</hi> Advice, forged by <hi>Vergerius</hi> or ſome other Heretic againſt the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The difference between that Advice of Nine to <hi>Paul,</hi> and this of Three to <hi>Julius,</hi> is in ſome reſpects very conſiderable; parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in this, that the Nine ſeemed to be ſerious and were not, the Three were ſerious and ſeemed not to be ſo; which makes the Advice of the former look like <hi>Sincerity,</hi> and that of the latter to look like <hi>Wit:</hi> Whereas in Truth the one was very gravely given, without any intention to have it followed, the other with that pleaſantneſs and confidence that uſes to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst Friends, but with deſign of executing what was advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. But in this they agree, that as the Advice of the Nine repreſents the corrupt Practices of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, with the main Reaſons thereof, ſo that of the Three truly ſhews what kind of Faith theirs is, and how it is to be ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>Neither the one nor the other, that I know of, have yet had their turn in <hi>Engliſh:</hi> But they are ſo very inſtructing, eſpecially the latter, that I thought a few hours ſpent in Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating them into our Language would not be thrown away.</p>
            <p>They are ſo plain that they need no Comment, and the uſe that is to be made of them is ſo ready, that I need not make any Inference from them in behalf of the meaneſt Reader. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it ſeemed reaſonable to give ſome ſhort account of the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of the Times in which theſe things were done; which is all the Light that was requiſite for thoſe who may be ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the Hiſtory of theſe Affairs.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="advice">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95895:5"/>
            <head>THE ADVICE GIVEN TO <hi>Pope Paul the Third</hi> BY <hi>Four Cardinals, and Five other Prelates,</hi> Whoſe Names are Underwritten, in order to the Amendment of the State of the Church.</head>
            <p>MOſt Bleſſed Father, we are ſo unable to expreſs what mighty Thanks the whole Body of the Church is bound to pay to Almighty God, who has in theſe times raiſed up you to be the Supream Biſhop and Paſtor of his Flock, and gives you likewiſe that Mind which you have, that we have no hope ſo much as to conceive how great they are. For that Spirit of God by which as the Prophet ſpeaks the Heavens are made firm, has Decreed, as we cannot but ſee, by your Hand to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Church, now that ſhe is not only leaning, but juſt falling headlong into Ruin; nay, to advance her to her ancient Eminence, and to reſtore her to her former Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:95895:6"/>
            <p> It is no uncertain Conjecture of this purpoſe of God, which we are enabled to make, whom your Holineſs called to you and required, that without any regard had to you, or to any one elſe, we ſhould ſignifie to you what thoſe Abuſes are, and moſt grievous Diſtempers wherewith the Church of God, and eſpecially the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> has for a long time been affected, whereby alſo it has come to paſs, that theſe peſtilent Diſeaſes growing to their height by little and little, the Church as we ſee is upon the very brink of Ruin. And becauſe your Holineſs (being taught by the Divine Spirit, who, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays, does with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out noiſe of Words ſpeak in the Heart) very well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands this to be the Original of theſe Miſchiefs; that ſome Popes your Predeceſſours, having itching Ears, as ſays the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> heaped up Teachers after their own Luſts, not to learn from them, what they ought to do, but that they ſhould take pains and employ their Wit to find out ways how it might be lawful for them to do what they pleaſed: To which we may add, that as the Shadow follows the Body, ſo Flattery follows Greatneſs, and Truth can hardly find any way to the Ears of Princes; hence it has come to paſs, that there have been Doctors e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ready to maintain, that all Benefices being the Pope's, and the Lord having a Right to Sell what is his own, it muſt neceſſarily follow, that the Pope is not capable of the Guilt of <hi>Simony;</hi> inſomuch, that the Pope's Will and Pleaſure whatever it be, muſt needs be the Rule for all that he does; which doubtleſs would end in believing every thing lawful that he had a mind to do.</p>
            <p>From this Source, as from the <hi>Trojan</hi>-Horſe, thoſe ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Abuſes, and ſuch mortal Diſeaſes, have broken forth into the Church of God, which have reduced her, as we ſee, almoſt to a State of Deſparation: The ſame of theſe things having come to the Ears even of Infidels (let your Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs believe us ſpeaking what we know) who deride Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95895:6"/>more for this, then for any thing elſe; ſo that through our ſelves, we muſt needs ſay through our ſelves, the Name of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is blaſphemed amongſt the Nations. As for you moſt Holy Father, for ſo in truth you are, beſides that Prudence which you ſo long ſince have obtained, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo inſtructed by the Spirit of God, when you gave your ſelf wholly to this care, that the Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> wherewith you are entruſted, might be healed of her Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, and recover a good ſtate of Health, you ſaw, and you ſaw aright, that where the Diſeaſe grew at firſt, there the Remedy muſt begin: And following the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> you intended to be a Diſpenſer, and not a Lord, but to be found faithful in the Lord, like that Servant in the Goſpel, whom the Lord ſet over his Family, to give them their Food in their ſeaſon; And in order to this, you reſolved at no hand to Will that which is unlawful, nor to deſire the Power of doing what you ought not. For theſe Reaſons you called us to your ſelf, who how unqualified ſoever we may be, in point of skill, for ſo weighty an Affair, do not yet want a good Affection towards the Honour and Glory of your Holineſs, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all to the Reformation of the Church of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> You enjoyned us with moſt ſerious expreſſions, that we ſhould go and bring together all thoſe Abuſes, and lay them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, proteſting that if we proceeded herein negligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and unfaithfully, the account that ſhould be given to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God of this matter committed to our Truſt, ſhould be upon our ſelves. And that all things might be more freely handled by us, and opened to you afterward, you bound us by an Oath, and under the Penalty of Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that we ſhould diſcover no part of this our Truſt to any one whatſoever.</p>
            <p>We therefore in obedience to your Command, have brought together thoſe Diſtempers, in as few Words as may be, and their Remedies, the moſt effectual, at leaſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95895:7"/>which we for our part could think upon. And now we rely upon your Goodneſs and Wiſdom to mend all thoſe faults and ſupply all thoſe defects of the performance which are left in it, by reaſon of our incompetency for this undertaking.</p>
            <p>But to reduce all our Thoughts to ſome certain Heads; ſince your Holineſs is both the Prince of theſe Provinces, which are the Eccleſiaſtic Eſtate and Territory, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al the Governour of the Univerſal Church, and likewiſe the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> we have not taken upon our ſelves to ſpeak of thoſe things which concern that Principality, which by your Prudence is ſo excellently Govern'd as we ſee. We will touch upon theſe matters only that belong to the Office of the Univerſal Paſtor, and ſome alſo that are proper to the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all then we think moſt B. Father, according to what <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſays in his <hi>Politicks,</hi> that as in every other Commonwealth, ſo in the Eccleſiaſtic Government of the Church of <hi>Christ,</hi> it ſhould be eſteemed the principal Law of All, that Laws ſhould be obſerved as much as is poſſible; and that it be not lawful to Diſpenſe with the Laws, but for a Cauſe urgent and neceſſary. For no Cuſtom intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into a Commonwealth, can be more pernicious, than inobſervance of Laws, which our Anceſtors thought were religiouſly to be kept, and doubted not to call their Authority Venerable and Divine. All theſe things you know Moſt Excellent Pope, you have read them long ſince in the Philoſophers and Divines. But one thing there is of moment next to this, or rather of far greater conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence as we think, that it is not lawful for the Pope who is <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Vicar, to make any Gain to himſelf of the uſe of the Keys, of the power of the Keys we ſay, which <hi>Christ</hi> hath committed to him. For this is the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Chriſt: Freely ye have received, Freely give.</hi> Theſe things being in the firſt place provided for, ſince your Holineſs has the care of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Church upon you, ſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95895:7"/>that it may be furniſhed with divers Miniſters, by whom that truſt is to be diſcharged, and that theſe are all the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy to whom Divine Service is committed, the Presbyters eſpecially, and thoſe of them chiefly that have the care of Souls, and above all the Biſhops; it follows, that in order to a right Proceeding in this Government, the firſt care that is to be taken, is, that theſe Miniſters be ſuch that are fit for the Duties of their Function.</p>
            <p>And here the firſt Abuſe in this kind, is, that in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of Clerks, eſpecially of Presbyters, no manner of care and diligence is uſed, but every where the moſt une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducated Youths, of the vileſt Parentage, ſet out with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but evil Manners, are admitted to Holy Orders, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Prieſthood it ſelf, thô that be the Character which expreſſeth <hi>Chriſt</hi> more than all others. From hence grow innumerable Scandals, from hence comes the Contempt of the Eccleſiaſtic Order, and hence it is, that the reverence of God's Worſhip is not only diminiſhed, but well nigh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed. We think therefore the beſt way would be, for your Holineſs to appoint two or three Prelates of Learning and Probity to look after this matter, who ſhould govern the Ordinations of Clergy-men, and then to enjoyn all Biſhops under the Penalty of Cenſures, to take the like care in their Dioceſſes. Nor ſhould your Holineſs ſuffer any to be Ordained but by his own Biſhop, or with the Licenſe of his Biſhop, or ſuch as are Deputed in the City. And every Biſhop ſhould provide a Maſter in his Church, for the inſtruction of the inferiour Orders of the Clergy, in good Learning, and good Manners, as the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires.</p>
            <p>Another Abuſe of a moſt grievous Nature, is in the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Eccleſiaſtical Benefices, eſpecially with Cure of Souls, and above all of Biſhopricks, the manner having been, that good Proviſion is made for thoſe who have the Benefices, but for the Flock of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Church,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95895:8"/>none at all. In beſtowing therefore theſe Benefices with care, and chiefly Biſhopricks, it is highly requiſite, that they be conferred upon good and learned men, who are able by themſelves to diſcharge the Duties belonging there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and who withal, are moſt likely to be reſident; for which reaſon a Benefice in <hi>Spain</hi> or <hi>Britain,</hi> is not to be given to an <hi>Italian,</hi> nor the like; which Rule is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved both in Collations, when a Vacancy happens by the Deceaſe of the Incumbent, and in Ceſſions too, whereas now no regard is had to any thing elſe, but the will and advantage of him that reſigns: We think therefore it would be very well, if one or more honeſt men were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to govern this Buſineſs. Another Abuſe is, when Benefices are conferred, or reſigned to others, that Penſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are to be paid out of the Revenues; nay, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he that reſigns, reſerves all the Profits to himſelf: In which matter it is to be obſerved, that Penſions ought not to be allotted upon any other account, but as certain Alms which ſhould go for pious uſes, and for the relief of the Poor. For the Revenues are annexed to the Benefice, as the Body to the Mind, ſo that of their own nature they belong to him that has the Benefice, that according to his Rank he may live honeſtly upon them, and be able to bear the charge of Divine Service, and to repair the Church, and the Houſes belonging to it; and that he ſhould ſpend what remains in pious uſes. For this is the natural em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of ſuch Revenues.</p>
            <p>But as in the Courſe of Nature, ſome things are done o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then according to Common Rules, and beſides the Inclination of Univerſal Nature; So as to the Pope, who is the Univerſal Diſpenſer of Eccleſiaſtical Benefices, if he ſees that the Portion of the Prieſts, which ought to be laid out in pious uſes, or ſome part thereof, may be employed for ſome particular good uſes; &amp; that it would be moſt expedient it ſhould be ſo, he may without doubt provide accordingly.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95895:8"/>He may therefore very lawfully ſet a Portion upon a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice, for the relief of an indigent Perſon, eſpecially a Clergy-man, that he may be able to live in ſome meaſure according to his Order. But 'tis a great Abuſe that all the fruits ſhould be reſerved, and that wholly taken away which is to ſerve for the maintenance of Divine Service, and the ſupport of the Incumbent: and that Penſions ſhould be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to rich Clergy-men, who can live conveniently enough upon the Revenues which they have, is ſurely a great Abuſe alſo, and both of them are to be removed.</p>
            <p>There is another Abuſe alſo in the changing of Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, upon Contracts that are all of them <hi>Simonical,</hi> and in which no regard is had to any thing but gain. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Abuſe to be taken away altogether, has prevailed in this Court by the knavery of certain perſons that are ſhrewd in their way: For whereas the Law provides, that Benefices cannot be given away by Will, becauſe they are not the Teſtators, but the Church's Fee; and that the Church's Patrimony ſhould be continued as a common proviſion in the behalf of all good men, but never grow into a private Eſtate: No little pains have been taken, in which more of Worldly Wiſdom than <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Honeſty is to be ſeen, to find out divers tricks for the eluding of the Law. For Biſhopricks and other Benefices are reſigned, firſt, with a condition of reſuming them; to which is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, a reſervation to Collate the Benefices belonging to them; with another reſervation to Adminiſter and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern. And ſo here comes to be a Biſhop who has not ſo much as one Right of a Biſhop, while the other is no Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop at all, who claims all the Right belonging to one. Your Holineſs may ſee to what a paſs things are brought by the flattery of making every thing lawful that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to be done. For we would fain know what this is, but to make a private Inheritance of a Benefice? Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cheat beſides this is invented, that Biſhops upon their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95895:9"/>Petition, have Co-adjutors granted to them, not ſo well qualified as themſelves; ſo that unleſs a man be reſolved to ſhut his Eyes, he muſt needs ſee that the Co-adjutor is by this trick made Heir to the Biſhoprick. Again, it is an ancient Law eſtabliſhed by <hi>Clement,</hi> that the Sons of Prieſts ſhould not ſucceed their Fathers in their Benefices; and this, leaſt the common Patrimony of the Church ſhould become a private Eſtate. But as we hear, this venerable Law is diſpenſed with: and we muſt not conceal what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very prudent perſon will by himſelf diſcern to be a great truth, that no one thing hath raiſed more of that Envy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Clergy, from whence ſo many Seditions have already happened, and more are at hand, than this turning of Eccleſiaſtical Profits and Revenues from being a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, to a private thing. All men had ſome hope before this, but now they are reduced to deſpair, and ſharpen their Tongues againſt this holy See. It is another Abuſe, that Benefices are diſpoſed in Reverſion, and occaſion is given to the Expectant to deſire another mans death, and to be glad when he hears of it: By which means alſo when a Vacancy happens, they that deſerve beſt are excluded; beſides the Law Suits that are hereby cauſed. All this we think ought to be mended. By the ſame craft a farther Abuſe is introduced: For whereas ſome Benefices are by Law <hi>Incompatible,</hi> and are ſo called, our Anceſtours intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to admoniſh us by the ſignification of the word, that they ought not to be confered upon one perſon; this too is now diſpenſed with, and not onely two, but more of theſe Benefices; and which is worſt of all, Biſhopricks are enjoyed by the ſame man: Which cuſtom brought in by Covetuouſneſs, we think ought to be turned out again, eſpecially as to a plurality of Biſhopricks. What ſhall we ſay to the union of Benefices for a mans Life, to avoid the incompatibility of them under this colour, is not this a meer fraud upon the Law? Another Abuſe has prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95895:9"/>that Biſhopricks, not one only, but more are collated upon the moſt Reverend Cardinals, or given them in <hi>Commendam:</hi> which we, moſt bleſſed Father, believe to be no ſlight grievance in the Church of God; in as much as firſt of all, the Office of a Cardinal, and that of a Biſhop are incompatible in the ſame perſon: For the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals province is to aſſiſt your Holineſs in the Government of the Catholic Church: But that of a Biſhop is to feed his Flock; which he cannot do well and as he ought, if as a Shepherd he dwells not with his Sheep: beſides, Holy Father, the example of this cuſtom does a world of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief: For how can this Holy See guide others, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect their Abuſes, if ſhe ſuffers ſuch Abuſes in her princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Members? For we do not think that becauſe they are Cardinals, it ſhould be more lawful for them to tranſgreſs the Laws, but that they ſhould leaſt of all preſume to do it; ſince their lives are to be a Law to others; nor are they to be like the <hi>Phariſees</hi> who ſaid but did not, but to our Saviour <hi>Christ,</hi> who began to do, and then to teach. And beſides this, Licentiouſneſs being the fewel of Avarice, the uſe of it is prejudicial to the Counſels they take in Church Affairs. Moreover, for the obtaining of Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricks, Cardinals do court Kings and Princes, their depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence upon whom afterwards, hinders them from ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their minds freely; at leaſt, if they were bold and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling enough to ſpeak, yet they would eaſily be perverted into a wrong judgment by affection and intereſt. We could wiſh therefore that this cuſtom were broken, and that all the Cardinals might have an equal Revenue, which would maintain them handſomly according to their Dignity; which proviſion we think might eaſily be made, if we would be willing to ſerve <hi>Mammon</hi> no longer, and would ſerve none but <hi>Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things being ſet right, which refer to the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your Miniſters, who are, as it were, the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95895:10"/>for the right performing of God's Worſhip, and the well ordering of the People in a Chriſtian Life. We muſt now come to thoſe things which relate to the Government of Chriſtian People: As to which matter, moſt holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there is an Abuſe in the firſt place to be corrected; and the greateſt care is to be taken that Biſhops eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, no nor Curates be abſent from their Churches and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, unleſs for a weighty cauſe, but keep their Reſidence: but eſpecially the Biſhops, ſince they are the Husbands of the Church committed to their care. For we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to God, that no ſight can be more lamentable to a Chriſtian man going through <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> than this ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the Churches. Almoſt all the Paſtors are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from their Flocks, which are almoſt every-where entruſted with Hirelings. There ought therefore to be a great Penalty upon Biſhops above all, and likewiſe upon Curates who are abſent from their Flocks, and who ought not onely to be cenſured, but not ſo much as receive the Revenues of the Church, unleſs for ſome ſhort time the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops obtain leave of abſence from your Holineſs, and the Curates from their Biſhops. Let ſome of the Laws and Decrees of Councils in this matter be read, whereby it is provided, that a Biſhop ſhall not be abſent from his Church above three Lord's Days.</p>
            <p>It is alſo an Abuſe, that ſo many of the moſt Reverend Cardinals are abſent from this Court, and do not ſo much as in part do any thing of that Office which belongs to a Cardinal. We think indeed that 'tis expedient for ſome few Cardinals to live in their Provinces, ſince thy are as it were the Root of the Papacy, that by ſhooting out its ſtrings abroad in the Chriſtian World, contains the People in their Obedience to the <hi>Roman</hi> See. But yet we think it were very much for the Intereſt of your Holineſs, to recal them, though not perhaps every one, to their Reſidence in this Court: For beſides that by this means they would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95895:10"/>the proper Office of Cardinals, the State and Retinue of your Court would be provided for, and the want of thoſe many Biſhops would be ſupplied, who ought to leave the Court, and return to their Churches.</p>
            <p>Another great Abuſe, and by no means to be endured, ſince 'tis a ſcandal to all Chriſtian People, ariſes from the hindrances and reſtraints that are upon Biſhops in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning of their Flocks, and chiefly in the puniſhing and correcting of wicked perſons. For firſt, there are ill men, and eſpecially Clergy-men, who by many ways exempt themſelves from the Juriſdiction of their Ordinary. But then if they are not exempt, they betake themſelves eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Penitentiary or to the Datary, where they preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find a way to protect their Impunity, and which is ſtill worſe, by giving of Money. This ſcandal, moſt holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, does ſo diſturb Chriſtian People, that 'tis not to be expreſſed: We beſeech your Holineſs, by the Bloud of Chriſt, wherewith he hath Redeemed his Church, having waſhed the ſame in his Bloud, that theſe foul blemiſhes be taken away: Let theſe miſchiefs be removed, to which, if in any Republick or Kingdom allowance were given, it would in a little time fall head-long into ruine, and would not by any means be able to ſubſiſt long: And yet we think it is lawful for us, ſo that we have the doing of it our ſelves, to ſee theſe Monſters brought into the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Orders of the <hi>Religious,</hi> there is another Abuſe to be corrected, that many of them are ſo degenerate, that they are grown ſcandalous, and their examples pernicious to the <hi>Seculars.</hi> We think the <hi>Conventual</hi> Orders are to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed, not by doing to any man that injury of Diſpoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him, but by forbidding them to admit any more; For thus, without wronging any one, they would ſoon be worn out, and good <hi>Religious</hi> might be ſubſtituted inſtead of them: but at preſent it were beſt, that all Children who
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95895:11"/>are not yet profeſſed, ſhould be taken from their Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            <p>We think alſo, that as to the <hi>Preachers</hi> and <hi>Confeſſors</hi> that are ſent out by the Fryers, there is need of Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion and Amendment, that great care ſhould be taken by their Chief, that they be fitly qualified; and then that they be preſented to the Biſhops, to whom chiefly the Church is intruſted, to be examined by them, or by fit per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and that without their conſent they be not admitted to the exerciſe of thoſe Offices.</p>
            <p>We have already ſaid, moſt holy Father, that it is by no means lawful to make any Gain by the uſe of the Keys: in which matter the Words of Chriſt ſtand firm and ſure, <hi>Freely ye have received, freely give.</hi> This does not onely belong to your Holineſs to take notice of, but to all who ſhare in this power; and therefore we deſire that it may be obſerved by your Legates and <hi>Nuntio's:</hi> For as the cuſtom which has much prevailed, diſhonours this See, and makes the People clamorous, ſo the contrary would be exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the Ornament of the one, and for the Edification of the other.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian People are diſturbed by another Abuſe, which concerns <hi>Nuns</hi> that are under the care of the <hi>Conventual</hi> Fryers, where in moſt Monaſteries, publick Sacriledges are committed to the intolerable ſcandal of the Citizens. Let your Holineſs deprive the <hi>Conventuals</hi> of this care, and give it to the Ordinaries, or to others as you ſhall ſee cauſe.</p>
            <p>The publick Schools are moſt perniciouſly abuſed, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in <hi>Italy,</hi> where many Profeſſors of Philoſophy teach that which is wicked; Yea, in Churches themſelves, there are moſt ungodly Diſputes; and if any of them are pious for the matter, yet Divine things are handled very irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently as to the manner, and that before the People. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, where there are publick Schools; the Biſhops ſhould be required to admoniſh the Readers not to teach Impiety to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95895:11"/>young Men; but to ſhew the weakneſs of natural light in queſtions concerning God, concerning the lateneſs or the eternity of the World, and the like; and to direct them to pious Belief. And as no publick Diſputations about ſuch Queſtions ſhould be permitted, ſo neither concerning matters of Divinity, which by this means would loſe very much the eſteem and reverence of the People: Thoſe things ſhould be diſputed privately; and other Queſtions in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Philoſophy, choſen for publick diſputations. Which caution is to be given to all other Biſhops, eſpecially of the greater Cities where ſuch Diſputations uſe to be held. The ſame care is to be taken about the Printing of Books; and all Princes are to be Written to not to ſuffer any ſort of Books whatſoever, without farther examination, to be Printed in their Territories. The care of which thing, ſhould likewiſe be given to the Ordinaries. And becauſe <hi>Eraſmus</hi>'s Colloquies are now-a-days wont to be read to Children in <hi>Grammar</hi> Schools, in which there are many things apt to diſpoſe uneducated minds to Impiety; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the reading of thoſe Colloquies, and the like, in ſuch places, ought to be prohibited.</p>
            <p>Now, beſides theſe things which refer to the appointing of your Miniſters in this care of the whole Church, and then in the Adminiſtration and Government thereof, your Holineſs may pleaſe to take notice, that there are other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes introduced likewiſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt concerns Apoſtate Fryars or <hi>Religious,</hi> who notwithſtanding their ſolemn Vow, draw back from the Religion of their Order, and obtain leave not to wear the Habit of it: No, not the leaſt appearance thereof, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome handſome Habit of a Clergy-man. We ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing now of Lucre, for we noted at firſt, that Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe was not to be made of the Power of the Keys recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from Chriſt: We now ſay that this kind of Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not to be uſed. For the Habit is the ſign of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95895:12"/>to which theſe Apoſtates ought to be held, nor has the Biſhop power in this caſe, ſo true it is, that this Liberty ought not to be given to theſe men. Neither when they have broken away from their Vow to God, ſhould they be ſuffered to enjoy Benefices, or Cures.</p>
            <p>There is another Abuſe in the Collectors for the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> for St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> and others of this kind, which put Cheats upon Ruſtics, and ſimple People, and intangle them in a world of Superſtition. Theſe Collectors we think ought to be taken away.</p>
            <p>Another Abuſe there is in diſpenſing with a Perſon in Holy Orders to Marry, which is not to be allowed to any, unleſs it be for the preſervation of human Race in any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where the Cauſe is weighty and of publick concern. This is eſpecially to be obſerved in theſe times, in which this Liberty is violently contended for by the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We conceive it alſo to be an Abuſe, to diſpenſe with the Marriage of thoſe that are in the Second Degree of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinity or Affinity, unleſs it be for a weighty reaſon. Nor ſhould Diſpenſations be granted without other Degrees, but where the Cauſe is honeſt, and ſtill without Mony; unleſs the Parties were married before, in which caſe it is lawful to impoſe a pecuniary Puniſhment, in order to Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution from Sin already committed, and to convert it to pious uſes, ſuch as your Holineſs promotes. For as where there is no Sin in the uſe of the Keys to be done away, no Mony can be demanded, ſo where Abſolution from Sin is deſired, a pecuniary Mulct may be laid, and deſigned for pious uſes.</p>
            <p>In the Abſolution of a Simoniacal Perſon there is another Abuſe, and 'tis a diſmal thing to conſider, that this Plague reigns in the Church to that degree, that ſome are not afraid to be guilty of Simony, and to go preſently for Abſolution. The truth is they buy their Abſolution, and ſo they keep the Benefice they bought before.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:95895:12"/>
            <p> We do not ſay that your Holineſs wants power to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give that Puniſhment, which is by poſitive Law appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for this Crime, but that you ought not by any means to do it, that ſo horrible a Wickedneſs may be more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually ſuppreſſed, then which there is none that breeds more Miſchief and Scandal.</p>
            <p>Neither is Liberty to be given to Clergy-men, unleſs for an urgent Cauſe, to diſpoſe of the Goods of the Church by Will; leaſt that which is for the relief of the Poor, be converted to private Pleaſure, and the luxury of Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>But neither are faculties to receive Confeſſions, with the uſe of a portable Altar, eaſily to be granted, for thus Eccleſiaſtical Affairs grow cheap, and that Sacrament alſo which is the principal of all the reſt. Nor are Indulgences to be given above once a Year in every greater City. Nor ought a Commutation of Vows to be lightly yielded to, but where the Good is equivalent, and will bear it out.</p>
            <p>It has been a Cuſtom alſo to change the Wills of Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, who have left a certain Sum of Money for pious and charitable purpoſes; which by the Authority of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs is transferred to the Heir or the Legatee under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of their Poverty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and this is gain'd by Mony too. Surely unleſs a great change happens in the Eſtate of the Heir, by the Death of the Teſtator, ſo that the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtator himſelf in all likelihood, if he had foreſeen that change, would alſo have changed his Will, it is an impious thing to depart from the laſt Will and Teſtament of the Dead. Of filthy lucre we have ſpoken ſo often, that we muſt mention it no more.</p>
            <p>And thus according to our capacity having ſummarily deſcribed all thoſe things which belong to the Duty of the Supreme Biſhop of the Catholic Church; it remains that we ſay ſomething of that which belongs to the <hi>Roman</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95895:13"/>This City of <hi>Rome</hi> is both the Mother of the Church, and the Miſtreſs of other Churches, wherefore the Worſhip of God, and purity of Manners ſhould flouriſh there moſt of all: But yet Holy Father all Strangers are ſcandalized, when they go into St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church and ſee what ſlovenly ignorant Prieſts ſay Maſs there, ſo habited and cloathed that they could not appear cleanly in a naſty Houſe. This is ſo mighty an offence to All, that the moſt Reverend the <hi>Arch-presbiter,</hi> and the <hi>Poenitentiary</hi> are to take care of this Thing, and remove the Scandal: And the like order is to be taken in other Churches.</p>
            <p>Nay, in this City, Whores walk about as if they were goodly Matrons, or they ride upon Mules, and are at Noon-day followed up and down by men of the beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in the Families of Cardinals, and by Clergy-men. We ſee no ſuch degeneracy in any other City, but in this, which is to be an example to all others. Theſe Whores live in ſplendid Houſes: 'Tis a filthy Abuſe, and ought to be mended.</p>
            <p>In this City alſo Malice and Animoſity reigns amongſt private Citizens, to bring whom to a right underſtanding, and to make them Friends, is a main part of the Biſhop. Wherefore ſome of the Cardinals who are fitteſt for this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, ſhould be appointed to take up Quarrels, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile the Citizens to one another.</p>
            <p>There are Hoſpitals, Pupils, and Widows in this City, the principal care of which belongs to the Biſhop and Prince. Wherefore your Holineſs may pleaſe to take a fit care about all this, by ſome Cardinals that are Men of Probity.</p>
            <p>Now theſe are the things Moſt Holy Father, which we for the preſent have brought together, as our Capacity would permit, that as to us it ſeems needful, they may be Corrected. But you in your Goodneſs and Wiſdom will make a more perfect judgment of every thing. We indeed thô we have not anſwered the greatneſs of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95895:13"/>which is too hard for us, yet at leaſt have ſatisfied our own Conſciences, and cannot but conceive great hope, that under your Government we may ſee the Church of God purged, fair as a Dove, at Harmony with it ſelf, and united into one Body, to the never dying Honour of your Name. You have taken to your ſelf the Name of of <hi>Paul,</hi> we hope you will imitate the Charity of <hi>Paul,</hi> who was a Choſen Veſſel to carry the Name of <hi>Chriſt</hi> amongſt the Gentiles. We hope that you are cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to reſtore the Name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> forgotten by the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and even by us of the Clergy, that hereafter it may live in our Hearts, and appear in our Actions, to heal our Diſeaſes, to reduce the Flock of <hi>Chriſt</hi> into one Sheep-fold, to remove from us that Indignation and Vengeance of God, which we deſerve, which is now ready to fall upon us, which now hangs over our Heads.</p>
            <list>
               <head>The Names of the Cardinals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gaſpar</hi> Card. <hi>Contarene.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Joh. Peter</hi> Card. <hi>Theatine,</hi> afterwards <hi>Paul</hi> IV.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>James</hi> Card. <hi>Sodelet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Reginald Pole,</hi> Card. of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Frederic</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Brunduſium.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Joh. Matthew Gibet,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Verona.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gregory Corteſe,</hi> Abbat of St. <hi>George</hi> at <hi>Venice.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fryar Thomas,</hi> Maſter of the Sacred Palace.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="advice">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:95895:14"/>
            <head>THE ADVICE Given, by ſome Biſhops Aſſembled at <hi>BONONIA,</hi> TO Pope Julius III. Concerning the <hi>Way to Eſtabliſh the</hi> Roman Church.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Most Holy Father,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOUR <hi>Legat</hi> at <hi>Bononia</hi> has given Us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that 'tis your pleaſure, That We, the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> lately Aſſembled in this City, by your Command, ſhould three by three, ſeparately conſult a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the moſt effectual means of <hi>Eſtabliſhing</hi> and <hi>Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eing</hi> the <hi>Apoſtolic See,</hi> which is at preſent ſo much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, aſſaulted, and weakned by the Perfidious <hi>Lutherans:</hi> And that we ſhould deliver in Writing our Opinions of this matter, that <hi>your Holineſs</hi> may compare them together, and deliberate with your ſelf about them as you deſire. We therefore, the three <hi>Biſhops,</hi> whoſe Names are to this, thô neither our Prudence, Learning, or Experience in bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, does avail much, will yet, in obedience to your Will, diſtinctly declare our Opinions, with ſuch ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that yet all ſhall be referr'd to the Judgment of <hi>your Holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:95895:14"/>
            <p> But in the firſt place, with all Reverence imaginable, We would admoniſh <hi>your Holineſs</hi> to take care leaſt the ſame thing happen to this our Advice, which we remember lately happen'd in another Caſe, when ſome Cardinals with Select Biſhops, Nine in all, conſulted about this very thing, <hi>viz. The Way of Reforming the Church:</hi> and preſented a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in which they offer'd their Opinions: For the things there, that ought to have been ſuppreſſed and concealed, preſently ſtole abroad, and were ſcatter'd and diſperſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as far as <hi>Germany:</hi> and ſo all our Counſels were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd and laid open to our Enemies the <hi>Lutherans.</hi> And theſe things were of wonderful advantage to them in the oppoſition they made againſt Us; and 'tis incredible what hatred of Us they raiſed by the Books they publiſhed upon thoſe Advices: Affirming that We our ſelves confeſs there are many Errours and Abuſes in the Church, which We are ſo far from being willing to correct our ſelves, that we do not ſtick to defend and maintain them by force, and perſecute with the utmoſt rigour any one that dares but to open his Lips about the neceſſary Amendment of them.</p>
            <p>The divulging that Council, moſt holy Father, believe Us, was a great diſadvantage to our Affairs; God forgive him by whoſe fault or negligence it hapned: But truly there ought to be all care and diligence uſed, that this our Advice never come abroad; otherwiſe we ſhall add affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to affliction, and heap evil upon evil: for We ſtrike at things of the higheſt concern, and freely without any reſpect of Perſons; we fall directly on the main cauſe; firſt, ſhew the Diſeaſe, and then offer a convenient Remedy. But theſe we ſay, are to be kept as Secrets.</p>
            <p>When we had well, and long conſidered, what was the State of this weighty Controverſie, recollecting all things from the beginning, (for we ſhould always run back to the firſt principles) we at laſt found it to be this: The <hi>Lutherans</hi> hold and confeſs all the Articles of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95895:15"/>Creed, that of <hi>Nice,</hi> and <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> This is very certain, for we ought not to deny (eſpecially amongſt our ſelves) what we all know to be ſo true. And theſe <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans</hi> refuſe to admit of any other Doctrine, but that alone, of which the <hi>Prophets, Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors; and wiſh likewiſe that all men would be content with thoſe few things that were obſerved in the Apoſtles time, or immediately after, and would imitate the Primitive Churches; nor think of receiving any Traditions which it is not apparent, as the light, were delivered and inſtituted by our Lord <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> and his Apoſtles. Thus do our Adverſaries judge, but indeed they judge ill: We on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand, following the Opinion of your Holineſs, would have all Traditions, Conſtitutions, Rules, and Ceremonies, which have hitherto been brought into the Church, by the Fathers, Councils, or any Private Man, (with a good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention) believed and received as Doctrine neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: But particularly as to Tradition, we believe as an Article of Faith, what the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> lawfully Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, with the Holy Ghoſt, has Decreed in the 3d Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>viz.</hi> That our Lord <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> and his Apoſtles, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered more Precepts, relating both to Manners and Faith, by word of Mouth, than are in the Scriptures; and that theſe, without Writing, were handed down to Us: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we can't prove this clearly, (for amongſt our ſelves we plainly acknowledge, that we have no proofs, but ſome ſort of conjectures, to make out what we teach concerning Tradition) yet we confeſs this to be true, becauſe the <hi>Roman</hi> Church maintains it. This, in ſhort, is the hinge on which the whole Controverſie turns; hence theſe Tumults and Contentions proceed. But we ought to venture all to keep their Doctrine from ſpreading any farther, althô it has got too far already, which in truth can never enough be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented: For 'tis no trifle that is under debate, but the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and welfare of your whole State, and of Us, who are all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95895:15"/>your Creatures and Members, is now at ſtake. For in the days of the Apoſtles, (to tell you the truth, but you muſt be ſilent) and for ſeveral years after them, there was no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of either Pope or Cardinal; there were none of theſe large Revenues belonging to Biſhops and Prieſts; no ſumptuous Temples were raiſed; there were no Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries, Priors or Abbots, much leſs any of theſe Doctrines theſe Laws, theſe Conſtitutions, nor this Soveraignty which we now exerciſe over People and Nations.</p>
            <p>But the Miniſters of all Churches (as well that of <hi>Rome</hi> as others) were willingly obedient to Kings, Princes and Governours. Let your Holineſs therefore judge how hard it would go with us, if by ill Deſtiny, we ſhould again be reduced to the Primitive Poverty and Humility, again ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to the wretched Servitude of being under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of others: This is therefore, as we ſaid before, a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the higheſt moment.</p>
            <p>Moreover, this in our judgment, is the onely way of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding this grievous danger. We find upon full examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the matter, that the Glory, Authority and Power of the Church firſt aroſe when ſhrewd diſcreet active Biſhops began to preſide over it, who uſed their opportunities to obtain from the Emperours, that they would by their Authority and Power Eſtabliſh the Primacy and Supreme Power over other Churches, in this See. And this Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the 3d, amongſt others, is ſaid to have received from the Emperour <hi>Phocas.</hi> We obſerved likewiſe, that the Affairs of the Church began more and more to flouriſh every day, when Cardinals were created, the number of Biſhops was encreaſed, and ſo many and ſo goodly Orders of Monks and Nuns were firſt founded. Nor can we doubt, but thoſe Popes, Cardinals, Biſhops, Monks and Nuns, have by their Cunning, their Inventions, Rites, and Ceremonies, turn'd away the Church from that ancient Doctrine which kept her ſo poor and humble, and have by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95895:16"/>theſe Arts procured her Favour and Authority. We ought therefore to take the ſame meaſures to preſerve her in that State to which they have raiſed her: That is, all kind of application and wit is to be imploy'd; the number of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, Biſhops, Monks, and Nuns is to be encreaſed, and to ſpeak particularly, your Holineſs is in the firſt place to take this courſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France, Italy,</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> (notwithſtanding the <hi>Lutherans</hi> boaſt that the greateſt part of <hi>Europe</hi> is in their Intereſt) are content with your Empire, the laſt of which does moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly obſerve all your Laws and Conſtitutions, does not change or innovate in any thing. And as for that Nation you need not be ſollicitous; for you can find but few a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Spaniards</hi> who have not an abhorrence for the Doctrine of <hi>Luther:</hi> But if there are any Hereticks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, they are ſuch as rather deny that the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> is yet come, or that mens Souls are immortal, than queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Power of your Holineſs. But without doubt, this Hereſie of theirs ſeems to Us more ſufferable than that of <hi>Luther;</hi> and the reaſon is plain, for theſe <hi>Marani</hi> thô they believe nothing of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or a future State, are yet wont to hold their tongues, or at moſt laugh amongſt themſelves, and in the mean time are not at all wanting in their Duty to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Lutherans</hi> do not behave themſelves thus, they openly diſſent from Us, and endeavour what they can to weaken and ruine our whole State. <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> ſeem plainly to affect Innovations; and moſt of theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, according to the Copy that <hi>Germany</hi> has ſet them, are ready to lay hold on the next occaſion to fall off from Us: Moreover, there are many eminent Cities in thoſe two Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, who have no Biſhop of their own, but are ſubject to the Biſhops of the greater and moſt powerful Cities. Now your Holineſs ſhould chooſe out about a hundred of theſe, and create ſo many new Biſhops to govern them. Then
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95895:16"/>add fifty more to the preſent number of Cardinals; and out of all theſe, Biſhops, I ſay, and Cardinals, as well old as new, ſelect thirty or forty of the moſt ſubtile, and moſt verſed in Courts and Buſineſs, who are skilful in the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non and Civil Laws: Keep theſe about your Perſon, let theſe be your Counfellors and Miniſters in your moſt weighty Affairs, and private concerns. And ſend all the reſt, as well thoſe Biſhops that are Cardinals, as others, into their reſpective Dioceſs: and order them to entertain the People with Plays, Shows, and all manner of Diverſions. And let them preſent themſelves to the People both in the Church, and riding frequently about the City, in as much pomp and ſplendor as they do at <hi>Rome.</hi> So will it come to paſs, that the common People, who admire theſe Pomps and Ceremonies, and are wont to make much Money where there are many rich men, will at laſt be brought o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver either by Courteſie, or their own advantage to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour your ſide: And we need not fear for the future, what <hi>Luther, Brentius, Melancthon,</hi> or that late Heretick <hi>Verge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> ſhall Write. Oh! how much did it concern Us, that he ſhould not have eſcap't from Us, but have here been ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther clapt into Priſon, or thrown into <hi>Tiber?</hi> For he who was brought up in your publick and private Affairs, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with a great deal of our concerns, and of all our Councils. But your Holineſs has long hands, and in your great Wiſdom will find a Remedy for this Evil: for it is, and ever will be lawful to take all ways to free our ſelves from the Snares of our Enemies; nor did we think fit to name thoſe men, but for a very good reaſon; a word to the Wiſe. Then let your Holineſs take care that theſe Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals and Biſhops that reſide in their Dioceſs, beſtow Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices on the Children of their Citizens; for this is an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and ready way to keep their minds ſteady in the Faith. And we know many of your Subjects who would long ago have embraced <hi>Luther</hi>'s Doctrine, but for this one
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95895:17"/>reaſon, that either they themſelves, or their Brothers, or their Sons enjoyed ſome Eccleſiaſtical Preferment. Nor would it be amiſs to ſend a great many of thoſe Prieſts that they call <hi>Chietini</hi> and <hi>Paulini,</hi> into <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy:</hi> For, to ſay the truth, theſe common Prieſts and Monks do really abuſe the Maſs too much, which they ſay with little or no Devotion, chopping it up in haſte, and making a publick Sale of it: Beſides they live ſuch diſſolute profligate lives, that men deſervedly give no longer credit to them, nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelves to be perſwaded (though our Sophiſters take great pains about it) that a wicked debauched Fellow can draw <hi>Chriſt</hi> out of Heaven to the Altar, free Souls from Purgatory, and obtain Forgiveneſs of Sins, both to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others, and all this by the <hi>Works Done.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe new Prieſts the <hi>Chietini,</hi> becauſe they ſay Maſs ſlower, and with greater gravity, take no Hire, but are content with their Meat and Cloathing, and in the courſe of their lives carry a greater ſhew of goodneſs, will reſtore Maſs to its Primitive Authority, and recover its Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. You ſhould likewiſe make it your buſineſs to get new Orders of Monks founded every-where: for they, believe us, do great ſervice in the eſtabliſhment of your Dominion. For you may conſider how they have encreaſed it by the Confeſſions, Preaching, and Worſhip which they have brought into the Church. Beſides, we are taught this by long experience, that the Sect of the <hi>Lutherans</hi> has been leſs able to intrude it ſelf there where there is the greateſt numbers of Monks (eſpecially <hi>Dominicans</hi> and <hi>Franciſcans</hi>) who have ever ſtoutly maintained your, and overthrown the Adverſaries Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe give Orders to the Cardinals and Biſhops who Reſide, as well as to the Prieſts and Monks, that they inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute new Fraternities, as they call 'em, in honour of this and that Saint. For our Brother <hi>Thomas Stella,</hi> or <hi>Todeſchin,</hi> boaſts that he contributed much to the Eſtabliſhment and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95895:17"/>Enlarging of your Empire, by Preaching the people in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parts of <hi>Italy</hi> into a zeal for theſe Fraternities, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that of <hi>Corpus Chriſti.</hi> Moreover, let them make Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications with the greateſt ſhow and pomp imaginable. Let them cauſe new Statues and Images to be made, burn Lamps and Candles before them, and uſe all ſorts of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments and Organs in their Temples, theſe are the things I ſay, with which the people are chiefly delighted, and for whoſe ſake they have almoſt forgot that Doctrine which was ſo deſtructive and pernicious to us.</p>
            <p>Nor are theſe which we have mentioned the only things to be obſerved, but the moſt Reverend the Cardinals and Biſhops, ought likewiſe to be mindful of this.</p>
            <p>That they themſelves ſing Maſs with the greateſt Pomp and Magnificence they can poſſibly, and alſo Conſecrate Fonts, Give Orders, Purifie Churches, Altars, and Bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Places, Chriſten Bells, Veil Nuns, in the Eyes of the people, and in the ſight of all the Congregation. For the vulgar are given to admire, and to be amuſed, with theſe things, in the Contemplation of which their minds are as it were ſo intangled in a ſnare, that they have no reliſh for any other food; or any inclination to any other Doctrine. As indeed (to ſay the truth) they were deſigned for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. And really in our judgment, theſe things ſhould be augmented and multiplied, for if the introducing and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing thoſe few which we have now mentioned, were of ſuch uſe to the ſettlement of your Kingdom, of what advantage would it be, were there ſome new ones added. For example, That threefold Oyl for the <hi>Criſmes</hi> and for the ſick is Conſecrated every year upon <hi>Maunday Thurſday:</hi> and that by one Biſhop, together with Twelve Prieſts, with that thrice Repeated Adoration and Salutation, with thoſe Exorciſms, with thoſe breathings upon it, and with that rich Balm which is uſual. Let your Holineſs appoint, that the Conſecration be not performed under five Salutations,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95895:18"/>and Twenty Prieſts. Command likewiſe that ſome other precious Liquor beſides Balm, ſuch as <hi>Manna</hi> be added, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we find it Rain'd that in the Wilderneſs, which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſervedly ought to take place amongſt our Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. Likewiſe as often as the Water of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated, it is cuſtomary to put Salt and Oyl into it, and to dip the Paſchal Taper thrice in it, and to divide it into four parts. Order that moreover, they mingle ſome Vinegar with it, for that was given <hi>Chriſt</hi> to drink on the Croſs; and therefore that ought to be of ſome uſe amongſt the Ceremonies. Alſo in the Dedication of Churches, the Biſhops are wont to draw all the Letters of the <hi>Latin</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> Alphabet with their Croſier in the duſt, Command them to write the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Letters too, if they know them, (though that does not ſignifie much, for they do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>Greek,</hi> and hardly <hi>Latin,</hi> and yet they can write it, and 'tis the ſame thing as if they knew them) for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſts Crucifixon, was written on the Croſs in thoſe Three Languages, <hi>Latin, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Hebrew.</hi> And whereas the Biſhops only Anoint the Palms of the Prieſts Hands, Order them to Anoint both the Palms and Backs of their Hands, as well as their Head and whole Face.</p>
            <p>For if that little Oyl has ſo much Virtue to ſanctify them, ſurely a greater quantity of Oyl will have more virtue for that purpoſe. Laſtly, when Bells are Chriſten'd, they make a Perfume of <hi>Frankincenſe</hi> and other <hi>Incenſe,</hi> appoint that <hi>Musk</hi> and <hi>Amber</hi> be mixt with it, to raiſe and increaſe the Religion of the thing, and the wonder of the people. Once more, when any Biſhop ſets himſelf to offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate in any Divine Service, with Pomp and Solemnity he ought to have many Ornaments to diſtinguiſh him from ordinary Prieſts: ſuch as (to omit the reſt) the Bones and Reliques of ſome Dead Man, which he uſually wears at his Breaſt, ſet in Gold in the Form of a Croſs. Do you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand him to hang a whole naked Leg, Arm, or Head of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95895:18"/>ſome Saint about his Neck, by a good thick Cord; for that will contribute very much to the encreaſe of the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Aſtoniſhment of all that ſee it. The truth is, theſe Ceremonies were all invented and continued by Popes; you therefore that are Pope, may if you pleaſe, augment them. Nay rather indeed, for that Purpoſe and Deſign which we mentioned, ought to do it. Beſides, we would adviſe, that your Helineſs ſhould lay your Commands on thoſe Cardinals and Biſhops that happen to reſide in their Dioceſs, that they take care to have <hi>Logick, Sophiſtry,</hi> and the Art of the <hi>School-men, Metaphiſicks,</hi> the <hi>Decretals Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> the <hi>Clementines,</hi> the <hi>Extravagants,</hi> and the Rules of <hi>Chancery</hi> publickly Taught and Read in their Cities. It had been well, if Men had ever applyed themſelves indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriouſly to the Reading ſuch ſort of Books, for then our Affairs had never been in ſo bad a poſture as they are; but deſpiſing this ſort of Learning, they began to employ them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in learning <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and in a little time to examine the Tranſlation of the Bible by the true Original, and to ſtudy Divinity, and the Antient Fathers of the Church; and hence ſprung all the Misfortunes we lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; therefore you muſt endeavour, that ſetting theſe Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies aſide, Men ſhould again fall to the Study of the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and of your Canon-Law, by which 'tis manifeſt, the ſtudy of Divinity was in a manner overwhelm'd and buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But let your Holineſs uſe caution in this: For we men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before only the <hi>Decretals,</hi> and <hi>Sextus,</hi> and the <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentines,</hi> and the <hi>Extravagants,</hi> and not that which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Decretum,</hi> which ought not to ſeem ſtrange. For 'tis a pernicious Book, and leſſens your Authority extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, although it ſeems in ſome places to enlarge it: For a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other things, in ſeveral places it denies, That the Pope can add the leaſt Title to that Doctrine, which our Saviour delivered to us, and the Apoſtles taught; for thus ſays the Canon, <hi>Transferat, &amp;c.</hi> 24. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <q>They change
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95895:19"/>Truth into a Lye, who Preach any other thing then what they received from the Apoſtles.</q> This is a down-right <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theran</hi> Maxim: for what elſe do our Adverſaries daily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcate, Then that it is not lawful to depart in the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, from thoſe things that were in uſe amongſt the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles? But who of us doth not every day often depart from them? Indeed in our Churches we ſcarce retain (as we hinted at the beginning) the leaſt ſhadow of that Doctrine and Diſcipline, which flouriſht in the times of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, but have brought in quite another of our own. Nay, we are expreſly called Lyars by that <hi>Decretum,</hi> inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as we have done this: yet we have done it by the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe and Inſtructions of Popes; nay by their peremptory Order and Command. But we wiſh there were not ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Canons as there are of this kind, that enjoyn things directly contrary to what the Popes, and all of us do eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day (we ſpeak of Matters of Faith and Doctrine, not of Manners.) Take one or two of them for inſtance. Thus ſays the Canon that begins <hi>Contra</hi> 25. <hi>q.</hi> 1. Nothing can be eſtabliſht contrary to the Conſtitutions of the Fathers, nor any thing alter'd, no not by the Authority of this See. And then another Canon, that begins <hi>Ideo, &amp;c.</hi> ſays, Thus by the Divine permiſſion we are ſo made Paſtors of Men, that we ought not in the leaſt to tranſgreſs what ever our Fathers in their Sacred Canons or Civil Laws have appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for we go againſt their moſt wholſome Inſtitutions, if we do not keep inviolably, what they according to Divine Pleaſure have ordained. Do not Pope <hi>Zoſimus</hi> and <hi>Leo</hi> the Third, (nay and the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Church) plainly here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare aloud, that the Authority of this See can do nothing againſt the Canons, againſt the Law, and againſt the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the antient Fathers, which ought to be Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly obſerved? How therefore ſhall we anſwer our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, when they preſs, and urge us with this, and turn that of the fifth Pſalm upon us? There is no certainty in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95895:19"/>their Mouth; for they accuſe us of lightneſs and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, who have ſuch expreſs Canons, which forbid the Popes to alter the Decrees of the Fathers, or to do any thing contrary to them; and notwithſtanding all this, thereis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more frequent than the preſumption of altering what has been Eſtabliſhed by the Antient Fathers and Councils. How, I ſay, ſhall we anſwer this, eſpecially ſince the Book of Decrees is ſo celebrated and famous, and is in all Schools, Courts of Judicature, and Churches, held in the greateſt Honour and Eſteem? And beſides, thoſe few which we have given you a taſt of, it contains a great many others, that favour the Cauſe of our Adverſaries, and favour it in ſuch a manner, that they ſeem to have been pen'd by ſome of them. Moreover, we ſhall conſider of ſome courſe to be taken with theſe Decrees, for it ſeems very abſurd, that any thing ſhould be taught, which is contrary to what your Holineſs does not only do, but commands to be done.</p>
            <p>But we have reſerved the moſt conſiderable Advice which we could at this time give your Holineſs, to the laſt: And here you muſt be awake, and exert all your force to hinder, as much as you can poſſibly, the Goſpel from being read, eſpecially (in the vulgar Tongue) in all the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that are under your Dominion. Let that little of it which they have in the Maſs ſerve their turn, nor ſuffer any Mortal to read any thing more; for as long as Men were contented with that little, things went to your mind, but grew worſe and worſe from that time, that they commonly read more. This in ſhort is the Book that has beyond all others raiſed thoſe Storms and Tempeſts, in which we are almoſt driven to deſtruction. And really who ever ſhall diligently weigh the Scripture, and then conſider all the things that are uſually done in our Churches, will find there is great difference betwixt them; and that this Doctrine of ours is very unlike, and in many things quite repugnant to it. And no ſooner does any man diſcover this, being ſet
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95895:20"/>on by ſome of our Learned Adverſaries, but he never cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes bawling againſt us, till he has made the whole Matter publick, and rendred us odious to all Men. Therefore thoſe Papers are to be ſtiſled; but you muſt uſe caution and diligence in it, leaſt that create us greater diſturbance.
<note n="*" place="margin">Author of e Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll ur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>D. John Della Caſa</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Beneventum,</hi> the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate of your See at <hi>Venice,</hi> behaved himſelf handſomly in that buſineſs; for although he did not openly and avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly condemn that Book of the Goſpel, or order it to be ſuppreſs'd, yet in an obſcure diſſembling manner, he inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated as much: whilſt in that long Catalogue of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks which he put out, he has found fault with part of the Doctrines maintained in it; particularly ſome certain Chapters which ſeem moſt to make againſt us. Seriouſly, a renowned Divine Action, what ever others chatter: for at firſt bluſh it ſeem'd ridiculous to many, that he ſhould condemn ſo many Authors at once, who writ about Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, when himſelf had never read ſo much as one ſyllable of Divinity, and Publiſht I know not what, to which he gave this Title, <hi>Of the Divine Art.</hi> But this is nothing, and they who cenſure this in him, have little buſineſs of their own to employ them, and ſhew themſelves to be great Novices in the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> For he, as he is a true and eminent Courtier, ſpake freely what was his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, which we think makes much for his credit.</p>
            <p>It now remains, <hi>Moſt Holy Father,</hi> That we ſhould in ſhort make a Reply, to what may perhaps be objected by you, that having done this we may finiſh our Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>Your Holineſs therefore perhaps may ſay, If it is at this time ſo dangerous a thing to hold a Council of theſe Biſhops, thô few in number, leaſt ſome of them ſhould dare to raiſe a clamour, and be ſevere againſt my Dignity to undermine it. How much more dangerous would it be, if beſides theſe therewere a hundred others Created? We ſhall offer three things in anſwer to this: Firſt, Look (as you generally do)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95895:20"/>that thoſe Biſhops, who are to be created, be ignorant and unlearned, but very skilful in the Affairs of Court, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to the intereſt of your Family; for that alone will ſuffice. Then avoid a Council as much as you can, thô <hi>Caeſar</hi> be very urgent, clamorous and importunate. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, If onely to ſave your fame and reputation, you deſire or would ſeem to deſire a Council, you may reaſſemble that. But (as has been hitherto) let there onely be admitted, who you are certain will go on your ſide, and let the others be kept out, and driven away. But of all things, be moſt careful, that no Embaſſies from any of the <hi>German</hi> Princes, who are of the <hi>Ausburg</hi> Conſeſſion, come into the Council. For, good God! what miſchief, what damage did we many ways receive by the Embaſy which the Duke of <hi>Wirtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> ſent to <hi>Trent?</hi> I wiſh <hi>Creſcentius</hi> the Legate had fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goted them up together, both <hi>Theoderic</hi> of <hi>Pliennigen,</hi> and thoſe two Doctors, <hi>Werner</hi> of <hi>Muchingen</hi> and <hi>Hieronymus Gerardus,</hi> as well as thoſe two ſcurvy Divines, <hi>Brentius</hi> and <hi>Burlinus,</hi> (for thoſe were the Duke's Embaſſadours) and ſo thrown them into the next River <hi>Atheſis:</hi> nor ſhould he have ſpared <hi>Sleidan</hi> the Envoy from the <hi>R. P.</hi> of <hi>Strasburgh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For ſince they could not obtain their Audience of the Council (and Hereticks are not worthy to be heard) they return'd into their Countrys with greater animoſity againſt your Holineſs than they had before: There they write Books againſt us, and embroyl every thing. It had been there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore much better Policy not to have kept our Faith with them (as our Canons order) but made them Inhabitants and Free-men of the River <hi>Atheſis,</hi> as an example to all other Hereticks, that they preſume not to come near our moſt Sacred and Holy Councils.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the things, moſt holy Father, which in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to your Holineſs, we thought fit to offer to you, being ready to have given better if we could: We truly have ſpoke freely and ingenuouſly what we thought: but we
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95895:21"/>muſt again and again put you in mind, to be careful that theſe things be not divulged. And if you act according to our Advice we have no ſmall hopes that your Holineſs will preſerve <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> (for as we ſaid, we have no appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of <hi>Spain</hi>) in the Faith, and eſtabliſh and ſtrengthen your Kingdom: As for <hi>Germany</hi> (to tell you the truth) we can by no means hope it will ever be reduced under your Command. Therefore we adviſe you to throw away all thoughts of it. For if <hi>Coeſar,</hi> when Victorious, after he had granted ſo many Articles, which are plainly repugnant to the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> (as you may ſee in his <hi>Interim</hi>) could not bring that Nation to an agreement with us; you may be certain there is no way left to regain it. Add to this, that the People in thirty ſix years are quite degenerated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another race: For they who were born and educated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Government, who had a ſingular ſence of their Duty to you imprinted on their nature, are dead: and there is on the other hand, a ſucceſſion of young Men, who as they had no experience of your Doctrine, neither love or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire you; inſomuch, as they do not ſtick (Oh Villany!) to call you <hi>Antichrist:</hi> We know there are ſome indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent good Scholars who favour us heartily, and really wiſh to reſtore thoſe things that were deliver'd them by our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, and re-inſtate you in your former Power: This they endeavour with all their might, and ſometimes ſcatter their Notions in Company, ſometimes publiſh Books to maintain and ſupport the ſinking Papacy. But theſe are much the feweſt, and of no authority or judgment, therefore they can do nothing. But 'tis wonderful to ſee with how much great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er vehemency and affection the <hi>Germans</hi> are carried to hear thoſe who teach the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Hereſy, than to frequent Maſs, or hear them that preach your Doctrine. Laſtly, All <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> ſaw the Letters of Cardinal <hi>Pool,</hi> your Legate, who is to veclaim <hi>England</hi> from Hereſy; who writ in this manner:</p>
            <p>
               <q>We ſtaid for ſome days at <hi>Tilinga</hi> and <hi>Ausburgh,</hi> and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95895:21"/>made moſt diligent enquiry into all matters belonging to Religion: But we found nothing of this kind that could pleaſe Us. For the Churches of our Adverſaries are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day wonderfully frequented, and their Preachers fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd with great alacrity: Ours on the other hand are forſaken; and if you ſaw our Churches, you would call them Deſarts, there are ſo few, and thoſe I know not who, old Men and Women that come to Maſs.</q> Thus he, and his Friends, particularly D. <hi>Aloyſius Priulus,</hi> writ a great deal to this purpoſe: In ſhort, we may deſpair of that Nation. Therefore your Holineſs may very lawfully exact ſomething more than ordinary from them who are ſtill your Subjects; that what you loſe out of your Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue by their Revolt, may be thence ſupplied. But we would likewiſe admoniſh you of this, that in raiſing Mony out of the <hi>Datary</hi> and <hi>Paenitentiary,</hi> as they call it, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Offices, as alſo in the exaction of Tithes and Tribute you uſe circumſpection; and tho you are deſirous to pick up Mony from every thing, yetcarry your ſelf ſo in it, as to ſilence the Clamours of People for the future. 'Tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain indeed, that all the Riches of the World are Yours, who are <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Vicar, to whom the Poſſeſſion of all things belongs, and therefore You may lawfully take what you pleaſe any where; but do this neatly and dextrouſly; for (let us confeſs the Truth) 'tis incredible with how great hatred People are incenſed againſt You, and what horrid things are ſpread amongſt the Multitude concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing You; and there has hardly been any Pope, to whom both in Words and Writing, they have more manifeſtly declared their Averſion. For, as for <hi>England,</hi> upon which You value your ſelf ſo much, as if it were to be aſcrib'd to your good Fortune, that that Queen takes care to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate Hereſie out of the Kingdom: You have certainly no ſhare in that Praiſe. Then We ſear leaſt that ſudden Felicity ſhould not be laſting. Beſides, the Queen ſtiles
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95895:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>her ſelf Supream Head of that Kingdom, next, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after Chriſt; ſo that, tho the old Worſhip and Ceremonies were never ſo much reſtor'd, Your Power and Authority is not to be retrieved: In ſhort, You muſt be very watchful, and face the Storm, unleſs You are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to venture all at one Caſt.</p>
            <p>Wiſhing Your Holineſs all Health, We humbly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, Kiſs your Sacred Feet.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Holineſs's most Devoted Servants and Creatures.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Vincentius de Durantibus, <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Termulae.</item>
                     <item>Giles Talceta, <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Caprulae.</item>
                     <item>Gerards Burdragus, <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Theſſalonica.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Bononia,</hi> 
                  <date>Oct. 20, 1553.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
